Guide to the Robert Calvert Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Robert Calvert Papers
1970-1995
1987-1994
The Wittliff Collections
Calvert, Robert A.
SWWC.065
3.5 Linear Feet
7 boxes
This collection contains annotated typescripts and page proofs of Robert A. Calvert's collaborative book projects focusing on Texas history and culture.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Calvert, 1994-1995
Biographical Notes
Dr. Robert A. Calvert was born in 1933 in Stephenville, Texas. Calvert earned undergraduate and masters degrees in history from North Texas State University, where he taught history from 1967-1973. Calvert also taught at the University of Texas at Austin, where he received his Ph.D. in history, from 1973-75. In 1975, Calvert then relocated to Texas A & M, where he taught and further developed his specialization in the history of Texas and the New South until the time of his death. Many of his texts on ethnic and labor history, 20th century Texas, and the Progressive Movement in the South were required reading for college level Texas history courses. In addition to teaching and writing during his tenure at Texas A & M, Dr. Calvert served as coordinator of history graduate studies, was a member of the TAMU Press' Faculty Advisory Committee, and co-editor of the Press' Southwestern Studies series. Dr. Calvert contributed to the Handbook of Texas, consulted on numerous Texas history related projects, and served as president of the Texas State Historical Association. He died November 30, 2000, at home in College Station, Texas.
Books Published:
The Dallas Cowboys and the NFL Chipman, Donald E; Campbell, Randolph; Calvert, Robert. Norman, University of Oklahoma Press, 1970.
Chicano: the evolution of a people. Rosaldo, Renato, comp.; Calvert, Robert A.; Seligmann, Gustav L. Minneapolis, Winston 1973.
Texas Vistas: selections from the Southwestern historical quarterly. Wooster, Ralph A.; Calvert, Robert A. Austin: Texas State Historical Association: Center for Studies in Texas History, University of Texas at Austin, 1980.
Black Leaders: Texans for their times. Barr, Alwyn; Calvert, Robert A.Austin, TX: Texas State Historical Association, 1981.
W.R. Strong: his memoirs. Strong, W. R. 1833-1916. Gunter, P. A. Y.; Calvert, Robert A. Denton, TX: Terrill Wheeler Printing for the Denton County Historical Commission, 1982.
The History of Texas. Calvert, Robert A.; De León, Arnoldo. Arlington Heights, IL: H. Davidson, 1990.
Texas History and the Move into the Twenty-First Century. Buenger, Walter L.; Calvert, Robert A. Austin, TX: Texas Committee for the Humanities, 1990.
Texas Through Time: evolving interpretations. Buenger, Walter L.; Calvert, Robert A. College Station: Texas A&M University Press, 1991.
Cartooning Texas: one hundred years of cartoon art in the Lone Star State. Forman, Maury B.; Calvert, Robert A. College Station, TX: Texas A&M University Press, 1993.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of these papers is comprised of annotated typescripts and page proofs of Dr. Calvert's collaborative book projects focusing on Texas history and culture. A small amount of editorial correspondence exists for some books. Dates range from 1970-1994, bulk dates 1987-1994
Historians -- Texas; College teachers; Authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Calvert, Robert A.
- Articles, 1970-1988
  Series Description
  Contains research, drafts, and a published copy of the article "Nineteenth-Century Farmers, Cotton, and Prosperity"
  - "Nineteenth-Century Farmers, Cotton, and Prosperity", 1970-1988
    - Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - As published in Southern Historical Quarterly, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Flyer for symposium at Texas A & M, October 8, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Books, 1970-1994
  This series is the largest of the series, and is comprised mainly of annotated typescripts and page proofs of books written by or edited by Robert Calvert. Publications are arranged in order by publication date, and range in date from 1970-1994, bulk dates 1987-1994. While most books are represented almost exclusively by typescripts and page proofs, files for Texas History and the Move into the 21st Century (Calvert and Buenger, eds., 1990) also include correspondence and reports related to the grant which funded the book, and some editorial correspondence.
  - The Dallas Cowboys and the NFL (by Donald E Chipman; Randolph Campbell; Robert Calvert), 1970
    - Annotated galleys, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Photos, b/w (60), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - History of Texas, 1989-1990
    - Galleys, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and suggestions for 2nd edition, from Dr. Arnoldo De Leon and Dr. Gregg Cantrell, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Texas History and the Move into the 21st Century, Calvert and Buenger, eds., 1987-1990
    - Texas Council on the Humanities grant - Application and related correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
    - Texas Council on the Humanities grant - Grant reports and records of expenditures, 1987-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Drafts: First editing of essays (correspondence), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Drafts: Introduction, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Drafts: Barr, Alwyn: Afro-Americans in Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Drafts: Chipman, Donald E.: Spanish Texas, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Drafts: Davis, Ronald L.: 20th Century Cultural Life, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Drafts: DeLeon, Arnoldo: Texas Mexicans, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Drafts: Downs, Fane: Texas Women, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Drafts: Hendrickson, Kenneth E., Jr.: Texas Politics, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Drafts: Lack, Paul D.: Revolution & the Republic, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Drafts: Miller, Char: Texas Cities, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Drafts: Table of Contents, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Consent to publish essays forms, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence regarding page proofs, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Review, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Texas Through Time, Calvert and Buenger, eds., 1989-1992, undated
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Annotated typescripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 6-9, Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Annotated typescripts, with stamped pg numbers, undated (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
    - Page proof set, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Page proof set, annotated, November 14, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Page proof set, annotated, January 17, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Page proof sets, lightly annotated, undated (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Reviews, 1991-1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Cartooning Texas, 1993
    - Annotated typescrip, April 5, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Numbered cartoons, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Page proofs, heavily annotated, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Page proofs, master revised pages, August 23, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Page proofs, lightly annotated, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Page proofs, lightly annotated "Maury", undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Page proofs, lightly annotated "Bob", undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Consulting projects, 1994
  Scope and Contents
  Dr. Calvert has served as an historical consultant to publishers and to historical associations, as the two files of examples in this series show.
  - Texas Maritime Museum - Correspondence and notes, August-September, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Critique of book prospectus by William A. Link and Marjorie Wheeler, November, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1977-1995
  The smallest of the series, this file of correspondence includes three letters relating to book orders and other routine, non-editorial matters.
  - Three letters relating to book orders and other routine, non-editorial matters (Box 8, Folder 5)